<rss xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" version="2.0"><channel><title>health++ team - health++</title><description>A repository of thoughts from health++ events</description><link>http://localhost:2368/</link><generator>Ghost 0.5</generator><lastBuildDate>Tue, 10 Feb 2015 22:19:15 GMT</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="http://localhost:2368/author/health/rss/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><ttl>60</ttl><item><title>Incentives and Financial Returns</title><description>&lt;p&gt;At our inaugural think-tank discussion, we hosted Evan Anderson, a 2004 graduate of the &lt;a href="http://localhost:2368/thinktank-1/biodesign.stanford.edu/"&gt;Stanford Biodesign&lt;/a&gt; program who previously worked at &lt;a href="http://localhost:2368/thinktank-1/spiracur.com/"&gt;Spiracur&lt;/a&gt; and the FDA. He currently works as a medical device consultant and is in the process of starting a new venture in dermatology.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To kick off our discussion, Evan posed this question:  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Are the financial returns for investing in a healthcare startup less than a technology startup? Why? If the perception is that they are less, how can that be changed?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In response, we discussed various reasons why the barrier to entry in healthcare innovation is so high:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Higher risk in healthcare than technology ventures&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Larger startup costs, including more gradual and costly user * acquisition&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Rules + Regulations&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Domain knowledge required for making a viable product&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Larger margin of difference between products required to convince care providers to overhaul any existing products&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Incumbant advantages in sales + marketing by the large players in healthcare&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We explored the incentives behind the current healthcare system and what consequences a shift from a pay-for-service model might have on the current dynamics within our healthcare system. In response to that shift, we considered what the implications would be if the heavy lifting of diagnosing patients were based on large stores of patient data - paying physicians only for the service of confirming a diagnosis and discussing its implication with the patient. We explored a number of possible future scenarios, and questions that health entrepreneurs will have to address:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Once we have enough data to consistently assess both care outcomes and patient satisfaction, what combination of metrics will be used to measure quality of care? This will be a key question in translating fee-for-service business models into fee-for-value ones, and in turn, these business models will be key to funding viable healthcare startups.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;How will extensive and affordable genomic data, along with advanced diagnostic algorithms, change the role of providers in delivering care? To what extent will technology educate, and how do we prevent information overload for patients? Determining the cost of access to and use of these technologies has huge implications for future health ventures.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;What is the potential for open lab space and more casual innovation for health tech -- is this the correct model for lowering barriers to entry?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The final thoughts of our discussion dealt with how we can start convincing VCs that healthcare is a field worth investing in. We considered two concluding thoughts on what might drive a change in the public and VC opinion of healthcare: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The rise and fall of a bubble in technology  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Combatting braindrain of new-grad student talent to the hi-tech industry by convincing students that healthcare is an field worth entering&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;</description><link>http://localhost:2368/thinktank-1/</link><guid isPermaLink="false">7eed5811-9190-4535-b161-ebe0e698836d</guid><category>thinktank</category><dc:creator>health++ team</dc:creator><pubDate>Mon, 09 Feb 2015 05:56:59 GMT</pubDate></item></channel></rss>