<rss xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" version="2.0"><channel><title>health++ team - health++</title><description>A repository of thoughts from health++ events</description><link>http://localhost:2368/</link><generator>Ghost 0.5</generator><lastBuildDate>Mon, 09 Mar 2015 18:53:09 GMT</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="http://localhost:2368/author/health/rss/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><ttl>60</ttl><item><title>Think-tank: Ron Gutman (HealthTap)</title><description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ron_Gutman"&gt;Ron Gutman&lt;/a&gt;, the CEO and Founder of &lt;a href="http://healthtap.com"&gt;HealthTap&lt;/a&gt;, joined a panel of students for our second think-tank discussion. Since its founding in 2010, the healthcare startup has garnered a national network of 66,000 physicians and curated a database of 2.7 billion answers to medically-related questions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The discussion was centered on the concept of telemedicine. We began with the prompt:  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;"How does telemedicine differ from traditional medicine and how will these differences evolve in the face of changing technologies and policies?"&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The group opened with a brainstorm on the positive and negative implications of telemedicine:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On the upside, telemedicine can:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Streamline the process of medical documentation; doctors no longer need to focus on written paperwork as information is directly inputted and transferred onto an online database&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Speed up the process of healthcare in general by removing overhead, wait, and logistical delays&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Enable patients to consult their physician anytime and anywhere minimizing time and geographic constraints&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On the downside, telemedicine could: &lt;br&gt;
* Weaken the patient-doctor relationship; the full spectrum of emotions can’t always be expressed via webcam. One attendee characterized the relationship as an “ongoing story,” strengthened by in-person visits, but not entirely replaceable with online interaction&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ron introduced the medical school's &lt;strong&gt;SOAP&lt;/strong&gt; mnemonic (Subjective, Objective, Assessment, Plan), the standard method of documentation used by medical providers. Where physicians have traditionally performed all four steps, recent advancements in machine learning have made it possible to diagnose patients based on large bodies of data, effectively automating the objective portion. &lt;a href="http://healthtap.com"&gt;HealthTap&lt;/a&gt;, for example, is able to use a patient’s browsing pattern on the website to help physicians identify implicit trends in health behavior.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The future of healthcare is certainly inextricable from data.  With this in mind, the group discussed the changing role of physicians as telemedicine becomes more and more prevalent. At first, it seemed that physicians would ultimately become full-time data scientistis. But the group soon reached the consensus that the imminent paradigm shift need not be binary. Attendees broached the idea of a physician also fluent in data science, a dual vocation that could analyze data trends while also maintaining the human connection. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The discussion closed on an optimistic note. Now that patients can consult doctors from the comfort of their homes, patients need spend time waiting in long queues, hindered by check-ins and documentation. On the other end of the spectrum, doctors are also able to free up more time for patients that actually require in-person treatment, while addressing more minor patient cases online. In conclusion, the group resolved that telemedicine has the potential to benefit both stakeholders, doctors and patients alike.&lt;/p&gt;</description><link>http://localhost:2368/think-tank-ron-gutman-healthtap/</link><guid isPermaLink="false">4927705e-86cb-4251-9f30-16976bfb7fba</guid><category>thinkta</category><dc:creator>health++ team</dc:creator><pubDate>Mon, 09 Mar 2015 09:28:30 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Think-Tank: Evan Anderson (Luma Tech.)</title><description>&lt;p&gt;At our inaugural think-tank discussion, we hosted Evan Anderson, a 2004 graduate of the &lt;a href="http://localhost:2368/thinktank-1/biodesign.stanford.edu/"&gt;Stanford Biodesign&lt;/a&gt; program who previously worked at &lt;a href="http://localhost:2368/thinktank-1/spiracur.com/"&gt;Spiracur&lt;/a&gt; and the FDA. He currently works as a medical device consultant and is in the process of starting a new venture in dermatology.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To kick off our discussion, Evan posed this question:  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Are the financial returns for investing in a healthcare startup less than a technology startup? Why? If the perception is that they are less, how can that be changed?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In response, we discussed various reasons why the barrier to entry in healthcare innovation is so high:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Higher risk in healthcare than technology ventures&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Larger startup costs, including more gradual and costly user * acquisition&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Rules + Regulations&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Domain knowledge required for making a viable product&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Larger margin of difference between products required to convince care providers to overhaul any existing products&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Incumbant advantages in sales + marketing by the large players in healthcare&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We explored the incentives behind the current healthcare system and what consequences a shift from a pay-for-service model might have on the current dynamics within our healthcare system. In response to that shift, we considered what the implications would be if the heavy lifting of diagnosing patients were based on large stores of patient data - paying physicians only for the service of confirming a diagnosis and discussing its implication with the patient. We explored a number of possible future scenarios, and questions that health entrepreneurs will have to address:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Once we have enough data to consistently assess both care outcomes and patient satisfaction, what combination of metrics will be used to measure quality of care? This will be a key question in translating fee-for-service business models into fee-for-value ones, and in turn, these business models will be key to funding viable healthcare startups.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;How will extensive and affordable genomic data, along with advanced diagnostic algorithms, change the role of providers in delivering care? To what extent will technology educate, and how do we prevent information overload for patients? Determining the cost of access to and use of these technologies has huge implications for future health ventures.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;What is the potential for open lab space and more casual innovation for health tech -- is this the correct model for lowering barriers to entry?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The final thoughts of our discussion dealt with how we can start convincing VCs that healthcare is a field worth investing in. We considered two concluding thoughts on what might drive a change in the public and VC opinion of healthcare: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The rise and fall of a bubble in technology  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Combatting braindrain of new-grad student talent to the hi-tech industry by convincing students that healthcare is an field worth entering&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Learn more:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Opportunites for students who want to get more involved with Luma Technologies, Evan's current venture, can &lt;a href="https://docs.google.com/document/d/1mffFrNw3pgAohan9gcKYdTz21b8apk7r0dw27c0M7X8/edit?usp=sharing"&gt;learn more here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</description><link>http://localhost:2368/thinktank-1/</link><guid isPermaLink="false">7eed5811-9190-4535-b161-ebe0e698836d</guid><category>thinktank</category><dc:creator>health++ team</dc:creator><pubDate>Mon, 09 Feb 2015 05:56:59 GMT</pubDate></item></channel></rss>